Rudolf Karl Bultmann Papers
Rudolf Karl Bultmann Papers
1929-1965
Bultmann, Rudolf, 1884-1976.
4.0 linear ft.
Papers of the German dialectical theologian. Correspondence, manuscripts (mostly in German), lectures, notebooks, and published material; correspondence includes three letters from Albert Schweitzer (1929-1931).
148875
Biographical History
Rudolf Karl Bultmann (1884-1976) was a German dialectical theologian. Born in Germany in what was then the grand duchy of Oldenburg, he studied theology at the Universities of Tübingen, Berlin, and Marburg; at the latter he was influenced by systematic and liberal theologian Wilhelm Hermann and New Testament scholars Johannes Weiss and Wilhelm Heitmüller. He received his PhD from Marburg in 1910 and shortly thereafter began teaching, first at Breslau and then at Marburg where he was made a full professor and taught for thirty years. His colleagues there included Rudolph Otto, Martin Heidegger, Karl Barth and Friedrich Gogarten. His History of the Synoptic Tradition (1921) is still highly regarded as an essential tool for gospel research. Bultmann was a proponent of "form-criticism," an approach which attempted to discover historical roots of religious writings. Bultmann held that "[t]he aim of form-criticism is to determine the original form of a piece of narrative, a dominical saying or a parable. In the process we learn to distinguish secondary additions and forms, and these in turn lead to important results for the history of the tradition."
[Adapted from "Rudolf Karl Bultmann" in Boston Collaborative Encyclopedia of Modern Western Theology]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Karl Bultmann Papers consists of correspondence, writings, memorabilia, printed material and miscellanea. Correspondence covers more than 50 years; notable correspondents include Albert Schweitzer, Gerhard Burgmann, Schubert Ogden, and Thomas C. Odun. Writings contains interviews, class lecture notes, essays, and books. Memorabilia includes articles about Bultmann, class notebooks, and material from Syracuse University. Published material contains two articles in German. Miscellaneous consists of a poster and audiorecordings (cassettes) from a Bultmann symposium,
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically; the exception is that of Albert Schweitzer, Gerhard Burgmann, Schubert Ogden, and Thomas C. Odun, which has been separated and arranged alphabetically at the beginning of the series. Writings are divided by types but are in no particular order. Memorabilia is alphabetical by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and Philosophy; Bultmann, Rudolf, 1884-1976.; Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965.; Dialectical theology.; Theologians.; Theology -- History -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Essays.; Lectures.; Notebooks.; Posters.; Theologians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Bergmann, Gerhard (Box 1)
  - Odun, Thomas C. (Box 1)
  - Ogden, Schubert (Box 1)
  - Schweitzer, Albert (Box 1)
  - General, 1916-1921; 1923-1924,; 1926-1932,; 1936-1943,; 1946-1964,; 1968,; undated; 45 folders (Box 1)
  - Interviews
    - Der Spiegel, "Ist Jesus auferstanden wie Goethe?", 1966 (Box 1)
    - TV, "Glauben und Verstehen" and "Theology and the Church in the 20th century ", Jan 9, 1969 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Lectures
    - Class lecture notes, Galather brief (Box 2)
    - Class lecture notes, Konuther briefe (Box 2)
    - Class lecture notes, Philipen brief (Box 2)
    - Class lecture notes, Urchristundunn, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Concepts of life after death - from primitive religions to German idealism" (Box 2)
    - "Der Christ liche Gotteslaube und der Moderne Mensch", 1963 (Box 2)
    - "Die religiosen Stromungen inder hellenistischen Kultur", 1920's (Box 3)
    - "Religions movement in Hellenistic times" (Box 3)
    - "Griecheneum, Judentum, und Christentum", 1930-1940's; includes notes; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - "Jesus Christ and the modern interpretation of the New Testament", 1951 (Box 3)
  - Books
    - Kommentar zu den Johannesbriefen (Commentary to the letters of John) (Box 3)
    - Kommentar zu den Johannesbriefen (Box 4)
  - Book reviews
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Korner, Eschatologie und Geschichte (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - "Geschichte und Eschatologie" (Box 4)
    - "Geschichte und Tradition" (Box 4)
    - Habilitation thesis, 1912 (Box 4)
    - Corpus Hermenenticum (Box 5)
    - "Exegetica" (published) (Box 5)
    - Faith, Love, Hope (Box 5)
    - "God and Salvation in Paul" (essay) (Box 5)
    - Humanism and Christianity (Box 5)
    - "Marburger Predigten", 1956 (Box 5)
    - Minor motifs in Paul (Box 5)
    - "Pessimismus und Optimismus in Antiken Welt" (essay) (Box 5)
    - "Reflections on Christian education" (Box 5)
    - "Reflections on Wilhelm Kamlah's Christentum und Selbstbehauptung" (Box 5)
    - Suffering in the New Testament (Box 5)
    - "Zum Problem der Entmy Thologisierung" (Box 5)
    - "Zur Frage nach den Quellen der Apostelgeschichte", 1958 (Box 5)
    - "Das Verhauduis der Geschichte in Griechentum und Christentum", 1960 (Box 5)
    - "Das Verhauduis der Christusbolschaft zum historichon", 1960 (Box 5)
    - Unidentified (Box 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles about Bultmann (Box 5)
  - Class notebooks, 1903-1904 (Box 5)
  - Class notebooks, 1903-1904; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Class notebooks, 1905-1906; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Class notebooks, 1908 (Box 6)
  - Class notebooks, undated (Box 6)
  - Poster advertising "Rudolf Bultmann Symposium", 1/17/86 (Map-case 99)
  - Poster, unidentified (Map-case 99)
  - Syracuse University, spring semester, 1959; mss. and clippings (Box 6)
- Printed material
  - "Staat- Kirche-Religion-Schule", 1919 (Box 6)
  - "Das Urchristentum", 1986 reprint, c1949 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Bultmann symposium recording, tape #1, 1986; bultmann_rk_001; audiocassette (Box 7)
  - Bultmann symposium recording, tape #2, 1986; bultmann_rk_002; audiocassette (Box 7)
  - Bultmann symposium recording, tape #3, 1986; bultmann_rk_003; audiocassette (Box 7)